Guide to the Elihu Thomson Papers
Museum of Innovation and Science
Elihu Thomson Papers
1864 - 1950
x
6 cubic ft
Thomson, Elihu, 1853-1937
Creation of this finding aid was supported by a grant from the Center for History of Physics, American Institute of Physics.
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Elihu Thomson ranks alongside Thomas Edison and Charles Steinmetz as one of America's most important inventors and one of the founders of General Electric. His legacy includes over 700 patents, with developments in electrical meters, high-pressure steam engines, dynamos and generators. In 1883 he helped form the Thomson-Houston Electric Company Electric Company, with his partner Edwin Houston and investor Charles Coffin. In 1892, the Company was merged with Edison General Electric in Schenectady to form the familiar General Electric Company.
Thomson, Elihu, 1853-1937
The Elihu Thomson papers were owned by the Thomson Laboratory before being transferred to GE's Hall of History, which then merged with the Schenectady Museum in the late 90s. The original arrangement and description was performed by the Laboratory, and that order has been maintained through the collection's travels. As some point, probably at the Hall of History, the collection was placed in binder sleeves. The collection is described to the item level, divided up into small series.
The bulk of Elihu Thomson's papers have gone to the American Philosophical Society (APS). This collection is modest and apparently arbitrary but with an interesting selection of materials that were kept by the Hall of History after the bulk of the Thomson papers were donated to the APS. These materials include correspondence, notes, clippings, scrapbooks and other materials created or collection by Thomson. They also include some addresses and articles about Thomson, some of which likely added to the collections after his death.
- CORRESPONDENCE, HISTORY OF GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY, 1897 - 1945
- QUARTZ MIRROR FOR MT WILLSON OBSERVATORY, 1879 - 1945
- HISTORICAL FILE: LETTERS, NOTES, EDISON REFERENCES, 1900 - 1946
- AMERICAN WELDING SOCIETY MEETING HONORING ELIHU THOMSON'S INVENTION OF ELECTRICAL RESISTANCE WELDING, 1924 - 1937
- LIFE OF EDISON IN RELATIONSHIP TO THOMSON, 1878 - 1934
- HISTORY of THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO. and EARLY LIFE OF ELIHU THOMSON, 1925 - 1943
- CURRENT THOMSON BIOGRAPHIC MATERIAL, 1890 - 1930
- EARLY RIVER WORKS AND WEST LYNN WORKS, 1907 - 1940
- PATENTS AND RELATED CORRESPONDENCE, SKETCHES, 1879 - 1935
- MEMOS FOR THOMSON'S AUTOBIOGRAPHY, 1879 - 1936
- "STREAMS OF INDUSTRY which in 1892 formed GE RIVER", 1868 - 1886
- ADDRESSES ABOUT ELIHU THOMSON, 1938 - 1955
- LETTERS AND DRAWINGS re THE 'GE MONOGRAM', 1899
- GE OZONATORS, 1911 - 1913
- GENERAL ELECTRICAL INSTRUMENTS, 1914 - 1920
- NEILSEN SURVEYS OF GE GRAPHICS INSTRUMENTS, 1928
- MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS re ELIHU THOMSON, 1886 - 1975
- PATENT CORRESPONDENCE, 1883 - 1915
- INFRINGEMENT SUITS ‑ PATENTS AND TRADEMARKS, 1878 - 1924
- ARTICLES BY THOMSON, 1920 - 1930
- THOMSON INCANDESCENT DYNAMO, 1878 - 1941
- GE PATENTS AND PATENT CASES against WESTINGHOUSE ELECTRIC AND MFG CO, 1881 - 1946
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1879 - 1932
- TRIBUTES TO THOMSON, 1897 - 1983
- ALTERNATING MOTOR METERS, undated
- HISTORICAL PHOTOGRAPHS & NEGATIVES, 1878 - 1927
- PHOTOGRAPHS of ELIHU THOMSON, HIS HOME and ASSOCIATES, undated
- INCANDESCENT LIGHTING APPARATUS, 1881 - 1893
- PERSONAL LIFE, 1864 - 1937
- European electricity, 1879
- THOMSON AND RICE, 1888 - 1922
- DATA ON OBSOLETE APPARATUS, 1885 - 1909
- OBSOLETE APPARATUS, 1873 - 1939
- ELIHU THOMSON - LIFE and INVENTIONS, 1873 - 1946
- PHOTOS OF WEST LYNN PLANT, 1888 - 1930
- SCRAPBOOK of ARTICLES re ELIHU THOMSON collected by AH Carsley, 1886 - 1889